Guide to the Consumer Reports. Henry Harap papers, 1916-1973 and undated RL.11810
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. Henry Harap papers
1916-1973 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11810
3.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Henry Harap was professor of education and author, co-founder and Board member of Consumers Union. The Henry Harap papers include clippings, correspondence, drafts of articles, lecture notes, meeting minutes, pamphlets, press releases and other printed materials that relate to administrative affairs in the American Council on Consumer Interests, other consumer advocacy organizations including the Better Business Bureau and materials pertaining to consumer education. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: American Council on Consumer Interests; General Files; and Printed Materials.
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Henry Harap was professor of education and author, co-founder and Board member of Consumers Union.
Henry Harap was born in 1893 in Austria; his family emigrated to the United States in 1900. He attended the College of the City of New York (now CCNY, BS 1916) and Columbia University (MS 1918, PhD 1922). Harap was professor of education at Antioch College (1923), Western Reserve University (1925-1937), and Ohio State University. He became Director of the Division of Surveys and Field Services at George Peabody College for Teachers in 1937 and served until 1959, when he joined the U.S. Office of Education. Harap was author of The Education of the Consumer (1924) and co-author (with James Mendenhall) of Consumer Education (1934). He died in 1981.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. Henry Harap papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports. Arthur Kallet papers
Consumer Reports. Colston E. Warne papers
Consumer Reports. Helen Canoyer papers
Collection Overview
The Henry Harap papers include clippings, correspondence, drafts of articles, lecture notes, meeting minutes, pamphlets, press releases and other printed materials that relate to administrative affairs in the American Council on Consumer Interests, other consumer advocacy organizations including the Better Business Bureau and materials pertaining to consumer education.
consumer protection; Consumer education; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; American Council on Consumer Interests; Harap, Henry, 1893-
- American Council on Consumer Interests (ACCI), 1952-1973 and undated; 1
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Budget, 1953-1968 (Box 1)
  - Conferences, 1953-1973; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Constitution and bylaws, 1953-1964 and undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1973; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee--Memoranda, 1953-1964 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee--Minutes, 1954-1968 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee--Reports, 1953-1969 (Box 2)
  - History, 1969; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Membership, 1954-1973 (Box 2)
  - Press releases, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Publications Committee, 1953-1967 (Box 2)
- General Files, 1916-1973 and undated; 2
  - Cleveland Consumers Club, 1920-1937 (Box 2)
  - Cleveland Housing Committee, 1932-1935 (Box 2)
  - College of the City of New York (CCNY)--Cooperative store, 1916, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Consumer education--Conferences, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Consumer education--Notes, 1936-1948; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Consumer education--Talks, lecture notes, 1939-1960 (Box 2)
  - Consumer education--Tests, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1973; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Consumers Union, 1935-1972 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Cooperative Distributors, 1934-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Institute for Consumer Education, 1939-1942 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Schlink (Frederick)/Consumers' Research, 1933-1935 (Box 3)
  - Dissertation outline--The Determination of Economic Objectives of the Curriculum, 1922 (Box 3)
  - Institute for Consumer Education, 1937-1941 (Box 3)
  - Joan Harap--Writings on consumer education, 1940-1942 (Box 4)
  - National Better Business Bureau, 1936-1967 (Box 4)
  - Notes, 1967-1970 and undated (Box 4)
  - Peabody College--Consumer education, 1941, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Peabody College--Education 424, 1940-1945; 4 folders (Box 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes guide sheets, examinations and other materials
  - Writings--Articles, 1922-1950 (Box 4)
  - Writings--Newspaper items, 1923 and undated (Box 4)
  - Writings--Papers, 1934-1956 (Box 4)
  - Writings--Unpublished, 1924-1925 (Box 4)
- Printed Material, 1932-1972 and undated; 3
  - General Materials, 1932-1968 and undated; 1
    - Alfred Hausrath, John Harms--Let's Investigate! An Experimental Approach to Consumer Science, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Alice Edwards--Scientific Consumer Purchasing, 1939 (Box 5)
    - American Home Economics Association--Consumer Buying, 1936 (Box 5)
    - American Home Economics Association--Standardization of Articles for Home Use, 1932 (Box 5)
    - Brooks Spivey Creedy--Consumer Problems and Projects, 1942 (Box 5)
    - C. Maurice Weiting, James Mendenhall--A New Consumer Grows Up, 1939 (Box 5)
    - Chevrolet--Go Get It, And Keep It! By Demonstrating Chevrolet, 1939 (Box 5)
    - Chrysler--Behind the Scenes in Chrysler Corporation's Engineering Division, 1950s (Box 5)
    - Curriculum Laboratory Bulletins, 1934-1943 (Box 5)
    - Curtis Fuller--The Motor Car in American Life, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Grand Rapids Herald Review--Consumer Education teacher's handbook, 1930s (Box 5)
    - Hanna Publications--Fraud and Answers Magazine, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Hazel Craig--A Guide to Consumer Buying, 1943 (Box 5)
    - Henry Harap--Next Steps in Consumer Education, 1939 (Box 5)
    - James Burt, A.B. ZuTavern--The Investigator activity book, 1939 (Box 5)
    - Jerome W. Ephraim--Consumers' Guide to Scientific Buying and Saving, 1933 (Box 5)
    - Jerome W. Ephraim--Ephraim Guide to the Scientific Buying of Everyday Necessities, 1934 (Box 5)
    - John M. Cassels--Consumer Education and Economic Efficiency, 1938 (Box 5)
    - Kaufmann Department Stores--Science in Buying, 1934 (Box 5)
    - Labels on Containers of Headache Remedies, undated (Box 5)
    - Lord & Thomas--Exhibit in the Case of Discrimination v. Business, 1936 (Box 6)
    - M.C. Phillips, F.J. Schlink--Discovering Consumers, 1934 (Box 6)
    - Mark Starr--Consumer Education & Labor, 1940 (Box 6)
    - Mark Starr, Helen Norton--The Worker as Consumer, 1934 (Box 6)
    - Runzheimer & Co.--Auto Cost Guide, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Twentieth Century Fund newsletter, 1939 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Department of Agriculture--Your Money's Worth in Sheets, 1936 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Department of Agriculture--Your Money's Worth in Turkish Towels, 1935 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Department of the Interior--Consumer Buying in the Educational Program for Homemaking, 1935 (Box 6)
    - W.A. Partridge--Science for the Consumer, 1933 (Box 6)
    - William Trufant Foster--Painless Debtistry, 1933 (Box 6)
    - William Trufant Foster--To Tell You the Truth, 1933 (Box 6)
  - National Better Business Bureau publications, 1937-1972 and undated; 2
    - 24 Questions for Home Owners, undated (Box 6)
    - Beware the Twister, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Central Air Conditioning, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Facts You Should Know About... pamphlet series, 1937-1965; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - FM Stereo: What It Is, How It Works, 1964 (Box 6)
    - I Want My Money Back!, undated (Box 6)
    - Invisible Enemies of Your Draperies, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Read Before You Sign, undated (Box 6)
    - Room Air Conditioners, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Safeguard series "Your Money's Worth", 1964-1965 and undated (Box 6)
    - Safeguarding Business and Consumers, 1938 (Box 6)
    - Self-Regulation in Action (Ralph Lee Smith), 1961 (Box 6)
    - The Boston Better Business Bureau: What It Is and What It Does, undated (Box 6)
    - Things You Should Know About the Purchase and Servicing of Television Sets, 1950 (Box 6)
    - Twenty Questions (and Answers) About Consumer Arbitration, 1972 (Box 6)